Serge Daney, take one.
Régis Debray: Serge Daney…
Serge Daney, you were born
in 1944.
We know you as
a moralist of images,
or a sociologist of the times,
I believe one of the best.
But we don’t know you
yourself,
you don’t talk about yourself
in your articles,
the times narrate themselves
through you.
And...
once you called yourself
a &quot;Cine-Son&quot;,
cinephile / cine-son,
as if the image has been
your ancestry, your family.
Can you tell us something
about the images
that looked at you
when you were a child,
and the way you looked at them,
as a child and a teenager?
I think the first image
that counted for me,
almost the definitive image,
wasn’t a cinema image,
it was the geography atlas.
I thought about it recently
and I realized that it was the image
that overlooked my childhood,
in the sense that at home
there was a map
which was
the map of the world.
Or the maps from school,
still very colonial,
all multi-colored,
with the idea that each country
is a different color
and the more names on the map,
the better.
I very quickly had an extraordinary
propensity to memorize names,
I think I’ve always known
the capitals of the world,
I’ve always known Honduras
was Tegucigalpa, always.
I can’t remember a time
when I didn’t.
All this to say,
that it was
the enigma of the map
that was the first image
that gazed at my childhood.
There were no images
at home,
there was no culture,
very few books.
The other formative space
was radio.
I am a child of the radio,
since there was no TV,
and still,
cinema came in third,
cinema was my mother
and my aunt,
especially my mother,
who would say:
“Oh, let's not wash the dishes,
we’ll do it later.
Let’s go to the cinema
and we’ll take the child”.
And so quickly
I was dragged along, joyfully,
in the neighborhood cinemas
of the 11eme.
There were loads of those cinemas,
a good dozen.
And I went to see the films
that adults went to see.
The only favor they would do me
was to go and see swashbucklers.
I loved swashbucklers.
I didn’t even realize they
were Italian then,
they were my favorite,
and my mother, of course,
preferred melodramas.
Actually, it was always Italy,
I realized later, much later.
So the formative,
in terms of images,
the fundamental image,
is the atlas.
So it’s not a face,
it’s not a portrait,
but it works as any true image,
like a face or a portrait.
Because any true image,
in the final analysis,
is a face,
and any face is a gaze.
So something gazed at me
from the geography maps.
I think it’s very important,
I’m glad I thought about it recently,
because it’s one of those questions
people often ask
and every one comes up
with their list
of the 10 childhood
unforgettable emotions…
No, I think the first image was the map
in so far as it was a promise.
It’s a promise that I,
grandson of poor people,
born at the boundary between
the 11eme and the 12eme,
where I live now,
so really a Paris kid,
1944, in a terribly impoverished
and disqualified France,
profoundly disqualified,
where the Algerian war
will soon happen,
I have the feeling
-maybe now
I’m reconstructing a lot-
to have been the child of those times,
obviously I’m not the only one,
and to have developed
very slowly
my relationship
to what we call images,
especially cinema,
under the auspices of an image
more important than all others:
the geography map,
the small Larousse atlas.
And then later
the bigger atlases,
and when I could buy the most
beautiful atlases, I bought them.
And for me no map
was ever complete enough,
and as soon as I found a mistake
it was discarded, and so on.
It’s a child’s thing,
it’s a visual thing,
because the map isn’t the territory,
as Korzibsky says.
But still,
from a certain point of view,
the territory looks
an awful lot like the map.
When you take the plane
for the first time,
you realize you could be
looking at the map.
And I believe that
the gaze of the map
upon me is programmatic.
Because it was always
the map of the world.
I wasn’t chauvinistic.
Really not, from birth.
So the far-away countries,
the weird and complicated names,
the strange drawings
made by borders,
the names that changed,
when Urga becomes Ulan-Bataar,
I have the feeling that something
happened behind my back,
I'm rather furious.
So for me cinema is the same,
it’s a promise,
a promise to be one day
a citizen of the world.
It’s a travel that continues?
It’s a travel that continues,
but it’s mostly the promise of travel.
I’ve travelled a lot,
thanks to cinema in fact,
film critics travel.
I also travelled
of my own free will,
out of fancy,
out of some kind of
mystique of the walker,
very fashionable
during the 70s.
But I get the feeling that
this promise was mostly kept,
because I’ve lived from it.
I’ve lived from
that world map,
it’s only now that it’s fracturing
and becoming politically obsolete.
It’s only now that I look
at the map of my childhood,
which in fact was Yalta
but I didn’t realize-
Now you have to take
the pre-1914 maps.
Yes.
Grandfather’s maps
are very good.
Exactly.
My map has run its course.
Today, I’ve lost interest
in geography...
That's how I realize
a life has gone by,
because whether Croatians
are independent or not,
whether they’re drunk on their
Croatian-ness leaves me absolutely cold.
That there’s a new country
with a new color
called Croatia or Slovenia
leaves me stone-cold,
whereas
when I was small,
really small, a new country
was like someone being born.
Whence the fact that it was
pretty easy for me,
as a kid, to be for
the independence of Algeria.
I didn’t have the slightest trace
of a political idea.
It seemed obvious.
It was like…
the more, the merrier,
and the more images there will be.
And anyway it doesn’t change a thing
since we’re citizens of the world.
And you can escape society
with images?
I.e. to find the world you have
to run away from home.
How does it happen,
this flight?
Is cinema a refuge, a protection
for the adolescent?
It’s well before adolescence,
it’s childhood, cinema.
It’s not adolescence.
It’s childhood.
It’s a much more intense,
much more
care-free feeling,
and much more serious,
of not being part of the world.
Or to only just be tolerated
by the world as it is.
And you know
by the age of 5,
like Duras
quoting Queneau
saying that a writer knows
he is one by the age of 7.
If he hasn’t written by the age of 7
it’s not worth pushing it.
It’s excessive, but true.
It means you know from the first time
you go into the courtyard,
on the first day
of primary school,
that there are people with
whom you won’t be friends,
and that there’ll be a group of 3 or 4
in a corner, the introverts,
maybe later, as for me,
the homosexuals.
In any case the cinephiles,
and they won’t share their treasure,
they know they belong to another
version of the world, or of humanity.